<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Balladeer - IF</title><link href="https://tundish.github.io/balladeer/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://tundish.github.io/balladeer/feeds/if.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://tundish.github.io/balladeer/</id><updated>2021-11-03T10:30:00+00:00</updated><entry><title>Balladeer in brief</title><link href="https://tundish.github.io/balladeer/balladeer-in-brief.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-11-03T10:30:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-11-03T10:30:00+00:00</updated><author><name>tundish</name></author><id>tag:tundish.github.io,2021-11-03:/balladeer/balladeer-in-brief.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p class="first last"&gt;This is an introductory article. Start here if you know nothing about Balladeer.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;div class="section" id="culture"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Culture&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You are reading a book. You are playing a video game. Culturally, what lies between?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In that space sits the Web and all its related technologies. We've had it for decades and it has served
us in different ways. It was a source of information. It was a platform for commerce.
It was a nexus for social and cultural messages. It was a surface for state and corporate surveillance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Web is a mature technology now. It is better than it was at the beginning.
Better to suit the big outfits. Better to serve the individual.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What has been lacking is a common understanding of why an individual would run his own web server these days.
The answer is as old as humanity itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to tell a Story.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="store"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Store&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Story-telling is at the heart of human culture.
Personal stories, family stories, folk stories. It is a natural instinct to tell them.
And now there is a free and modern option for those who want to do that in 2021.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Its name is Balladeer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="principles"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Principles&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Balladeer is 100% Free software.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Game logic is Python code.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dialogue lives in separate screenplay files.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rich syntax for text markup.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Story renders in pure HTML5 and CSS3. Javascript is optional.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Serve web-mode for the browser experience or run old-school in a terminal.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Balladeer helps you build web-native narratives for a decentralized world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="provenance"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Provenance&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Balladeer sprang from a project I did a couple of years ago.
I made a little puzzle game for a competition called NarraScope.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over two fortnights, in the evenings after work, I wrote the whole thing in Python because I didn't fancy tangling
with Javascript.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="A screenshot of the game Tower of Rapunzel" class="pure-img low-key" src="https://tundish.github.io/balladeer/images/tor-screen.png" style="height: 480px;" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's how, right from the beginning, Balladeer has hosted multimedia; images, audio, and video.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Added to that is support for computational narrative and parser-based interactive screenplay.
If you have a research interest in this area, you'll find Balladeer well fitted for that purpose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And this is where the power of the Python language really shines. I'm going to make a wild claim:
&lt;em&gt;Balladeer has the simplest, most flexible, most dynamic command parser in any game framework&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you disagree, please post a link to a better one in the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://disqus.com/home/forums/balladeer/"&gt;comments section&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="what-next"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What Next?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tundish.github.io/balladeer/category/blog.html"&gt;Balladeer blog&lt;/a&gt; hosts regular articles on how to use the framework.
They are tagged, so you can begin with the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tundish.github.io/balladeer/tag/basics.html"&gt;basics&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These projects are available to download, run and study:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/tundish/tea_and_sympathy"&gt;Tea and Sympathy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/tundish/pity_of_thieves"&gt;Pity of Thieves&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Balladeer relies heavily on other libraries, known as the &lt;cite&gt;Turberfield&lt;/cite&gt; packages.
Each of those has its own &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://turberfield-dialogue.readthedocs.io/en/latest/"&gt;online documentation&lt;/a&gt;. And you'll want to learn some &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.writethedocs.org/guide/writing/reStructuredText/"&gt;reStructuredText&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don't forget you can post comments under the blog articles, or raise issues at the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/tundish/balladeer"&gt;code repository&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have fun telling your Story!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content><category term="Blog"></category><category term="IF"></category><category term="basics"></category></entry></feed>